National Association of Black Social Workers, Capital District Chapter; Records apap096
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
National Association of Black Social Workers, Capital District Chapter Records1970-1991
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
National Association Of Black Social Workers. Capital District Chapter
apap096
17 cubic ft.
National Association of Black Social Workers, Capital District Chapter Records document the organization's history and activities with various forms
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Florence Frazier.
Administrative History
The National Association of Black Social Workers, Capital District Chapter was formally organized in Fall 1972 in Albany, New York. The National Association of Black Social Workers, Inc. (NABSW) was established in San Francisco in 1968 when a group of social workers attending a meeting of an established national social work organization disengaged from those meetings to form what would become the foremost advocacy group established to address social issues of concern in the African American community. The NABSW is designed to promote the welfare, survival and liberation of the African American community and advocates at a national, state and local level for social change. Headquartered in Detroit, Michigan, the organization is made up of over 100 member chapters throughout the continental United States and the Caribbean, with affiliate Groups in West and South Africa. Membership is available to persons of African ancestry who, regardless of profession, share similar concerns regarding health and welfare issues in the Black community. NABSW has over 30 student chapters at graduate schools of social work throughout the country. NABSW hosts an annual National and International Conference open to its membership and potential members.
Jerry Blanton was President of the Albany Chapter of the Northeastern Capital District Association of Black Social Workers in the early 1970s and described three goals for the organization. These goals included working with established organizations to unite the community, making the expertise of members available to the community, and accepting Agency Board Memberships throughout the area to enhance the better delivery of services to the community. This organization affiliated itself with the NABSW in 1972. The Chapter was also known as the Albany, New York Chapter of the National Association of Black Social Workers. The Chapter was apparently inactive for an unknown period of time in the 1970s and early 1980s before being revived in August 1983 by Deloris Kirkwood Brown. The organization sponsored workshops for its members as well as members of the community.
Scope and Contents
The records of the National Association of Black Social Workers, Capital District Chapter primarily document the organization's history in the early 1970s and the early 1980s. The organization's founding is well documented by meeting minutes, correspondence, and its constitution. The most complete documentation of the organization is for the years 1971-1972. The collection includes sporadic coverage of membership lists, legislative issues of interest to the organization, and programs organized by the group. The collection also includes single copies of the Association of Black Social Workers (ABSW) newsletter, the NABSW newsletter, and Black Caucus the Journal of the National Association of Black Social Workers.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection has no series.
African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Ethnic Groups; Social workers, Black; New York State Capitol (Albany, N.Y.); Administrative records; Constitutions; Correspondence; Legislation (legal concepts); Membership lists; Minutes; Miscellaneous; Newsletters; Programs (documents); Financial Records; Publications; National Association of Black Social Workers, Capital District Chapter; National Association of Black Social Workers
- Activities, Programs, Workshops, 1971-1973; 1983-1984; 1991 (Box 1 (National Association of Black Social Workers, Capi), Folder 1)
- Constitution and By-laws, 1983-1984 (Box 1 (National Association of Black Social Workers, Capi), Folder 2)
- Constitution and By-laws, National Association, 1982 (Box 1 (National Association of Black Social Workers, Capi), Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1972-1973; 1983-1984; 1991 (Box 1 (National Association of Black Social Workers, Capi), Folder 4)
- Financial Reports, 1984 (Box 1 (National Association of Black Social Workers, Capi), Folder 5)
- Legislation, 1981 (Box 1 (National Association of Black Social Workers, Capi), Folder 6)
- Members, 1973-1974; 1983-1984 (Box 1 (National Association of Black Social Workers, Capi), Folder 7)
- Minutes and Agendas, 1971-1972; 1983-1985 (Box 1 (National Association of Black Social Workers, Capi), Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous, Membership Certificate, News Clippings, Conference Registration Forms, 1970; 1972; 1981; 1984-1985 (Box 1 (National Association of Black Social Workers, Capi), Folder 9)
- Newsletters and Publications, National Association, 1971; 1984-1985 (Box 1 (National Association of Black Social Workers, Capi), Folder 10)